Hey, folks.
I'm Ben O'Shea,
senior reporter at the West Australian
and host of the Newsworthy podcast.
It's my great pleasure
to welcome you to the Western
Australian Museum Boola Bardip.
I'd like to start by acknowledging that
we meet today on the lands of the Whadjuk
people of the Nyoongar nation, and pay my respects
to their elders, past and present.
Now, before we get started,
just a bit of housekeeping.
In case you need the toilets,
they just back out there and to my left.
There's also a water station at the back
of the room in case anyone needs it.
And in the event of an emergency,
please
follow the instructions of museum staff.
Okay, so today
we have an extremely exciting opportunity
to collaborate with ocean exploration
nonprofit OceanX.
And this includes an exclusive live feed
from the research vessel OceanXplorer
while it's on a science mission in
international waters off Java, Indonesia.
And they'll be beaming back to us here
at the Museum.
It's truly
an incredible floating science facility.
So let's take a look.
Wow. I think that's
worth a round of applause.
And now the Museum is
proud to be presenting
the OceanXperience, an exhibition that
takes visitors on a journey to explore
the unknown outer limits of our oceans
and experience what it's like to conduct
mission critical science
aboard ocean access research vessel
the OceanXplorer.
Hands up who has
already been to the exhibition?
Okay, that's pretty good.
After this, I'm
sure all of you will want to check it out.
It's an incredible, incredible exhibition.
It's also a significant moment
for marine science,
with a strong contingent of West Aussie
researchers aboard the OceanXplorer,
including researchers from the Museum,
working alongside colleagues
from the University of WA and Minderoo
Foundation's OceanOmics team.
We're also pleased
to have the WA research team currently
working on Christmas Island,
joining today's live stream.
So a shout out to everybody in
Christmas Island.
It's great to have you with us today.
And just to give you all a heads up,
a bit later, you'll get a chance to ask
the scientists onboard the OceanXplorer
a question yourself.
But first,
I think we need to introduce them.
Dialing in today with us, we have
Dr Alexis Weinnig,
who is the science program manager
at OceanX.
Alexis is a deep sea ecologist
and marine scientist
with over a decade of experience
with a PhD in biology.
She has participated
in more than 20 oceanographic expeditions.
And also with us we have
Dr Jen McIlwain.
Jen is a science and research leader
with a PhD in marine
ecology as Director of Science at the Museum.
Jen leads strategic research initiatives
and multi-disciplinary teams.
Folks.
Can we get a round of
applause for Alexis and Jen?
We're very
excited to have you both with us today.
Alexis, I want to start with you.
Can you tell us a little bit
about the OceanXplorer whereabouts
on the vessel we are right now,
and can you tell us what your role is?
Sure. Thanks, Ben.
It's really great to be here
with everybody today.
We are in the sub
hangar of the OceanXplorer.
So the OceanXplorer
is our research vessel
that we operate and has multiple different
types of assets.
So, our submersibles
that people can get in and go down
to one thousand metres is one of our favorite ways
to explore the deep ocean.
But we also have other assets
like the ROV, which you're going to see
later today.
I am the science program manager
for OceanX,
so I oversee all of the science
that we do internally,
and then also bring partners together
to be able to do these awesome projects
like we're doing with WAM.
Amazing and, Jen can you tell us
where exactly in the world
the vessel is right now?
What is the significance of that location?
And then where is the expedition
going to take you?
So we're currently approximately
700 kilometres east of Christmas Island,
and about a thousand kilometres north west of,
the Northwest Cape in Australia.
Just for those of you
just to give you some sort of perspective
about where we are,
which is in the north-east Indian Ocean.
We're currently over
some really interesting looking seamounts.
These are literally sort of mountains
in the ocean from the seafloor
rising up to about two and a half thousand metres,
and they've never been mapped before.
They've never been explored before.
So this is a really exciting opportunity
for the WA Museum
to partner with the OceanX
and also other WA
institutions to explore
this just incredible environment.
And Alexis, just quickly,
what is that behind you there?
This is our submersible named Neptune.
So we use this submersible to go down
when we're working in places
a little more shallow
than where we are today.
These can go down to about a thousand metres.
They allow us to collect video
as well as physical samples.
So we have a suction sampler.
We have the arms that allows you
to grab things.
And that way we can bring samples
back to study them later.
Yeah. Fantastic.
Okay.
Who would like to see a bit
more of the ship?
Yeah.
Oh, we get a lot of hands up down here
at the WA Museum.
Alexis, any chance we could see the wet
lab where a lot of the science happens?
Yeah, sure.
So we're going to go on a little journey
to the wet lab.
So this is the space where,
when the samples get
brought back on deck after an ROV dive
or after a sub dive,
the samples get processed
by the scientists onboard.
And so that means
that they can be catalogued.
They can be preserved
and made ready for once
we get off the ship
to do a more in-depth analysis.
You'll see that we're walking around.
So this is within the sub hangar.
So we have both of our subs
as well as some other machinery
that we operate
throughout the different missions.
So over on this side we have our wet lab.
So this is where we would
bring all of those samples
and start to work with them.
So we're going to move these
right over here.
And so it's very exciting having
WA marine scientists from UWA
and Minderoo Foundation's
OceanOmics, and our own scientists
from the Western Australian Museum onboard
OceanXplorer
to explore these deep sea ecosystems.
They've been on board
since the 4th of July, undertaking
an ambitious research expedition
spanning the Indo-West Pacific.
The expedition aims to document marine
diversity across some of the region's most
remote and least studied ecosystems,
using OceanXplorers advanced technology.
The team is undertaking
careful deep sea specimen
collection with remotely operated
vehicles or ROVs.
As the cool kids say, these ROVs, see
sounds pretty cool
use ultra high definition 4K image
capture of sensitive marine habitats,
and they're conducting environmental DNA
or eDNA sampling
to better understand species
diversity and ecosystem health.
The expedition will also investigate
a range of remarkable underwater features,
including seamounts, underwater mountains
that rise thousands of metres
from the seafloor but still remain
hidden beneath the ocean's surface.
These geological features can create
unique habitats and act as biodiversity
hotspots, attracting a rich
variety of marine life.
Despite their ecological importance,
many of the seamounts and slopes in this
region have never been visually explored
or scientifically sampled.
Okay, I can see now we're at the wet lab.
So, Alexis, can you take us through
exactly what it is, what sort of work
you do there, and what role
it plays in the broader mission?
Yeah.
So when we
come into the wet lab, it's a space
that allows for bringing the samples,
whether they're still alive or they're
or they're ready to be preserved.
And so similar to what
you see here, I'm going to kind of hold
these up to the camera.
These are samples that have been brought
up from the ROV as Ben was talking about.
So from deep on the seafloor,
and by bringing these to the surface,
it allows the scientists to be able
to better identify, to know exactly what
species it is, and also to take samples
to sequence the DNA.
And that's important so that we can know
exactly what is the community on that sea
mount made up of, and what are, kind of like
the members of that neighborhood.
It allows us to really understand
the ecosystem better.
The wet lab is important
because it's a place
that all of the samples come to,
and they all get the expert attention
that they need
before we can take them off the ship
to bring them back to places
like the Western Australian Museum,
so that they can be worked up and really,
the scientists can spend a lot more time,
studying them.
Yeah, well, the museum's participation
builds on its ongoing partnership
with Minderoo Foundation's OceanOmics program.
And together,
the organizations are advancing
the use of eDNA technology
through the collection
and analysis of water samples
across Western Australia.
Jen, I'm hoping that you can tell us
more about eDNA, how you're collecting it,
and what's the significance
of this kind of research?
So we've got Lauren
here in the wet lab, and she's currently
filtering water that's being collected
and the importance of this particular
collaboration is that we're able to the
the OceanOmics team
are able to collect water at the same time
as we're collecting our specimens.
And what they're doing is,
eDNA is basically fragments.
All animals shed fragments of DNA
into the water column,
marine organisms.
And what they do
is that they filter the water,
collect those fragments, they amplify it,
and then they take the sequences of DNA,
and then they go looking to see
what kind of species
that, exist in the in the water column.
So this is really clever way
of identifying species
without actually having to collect.
But what we do is we're sitting alongside
the OceanOmics team,
and we're helping them
with the taxonomic identification
of those of, of that DNA.
So it's a really critical partnership.
And it's, it's this is the first time
we've been given the opportunity
to work together in these very deep
water environments.
I hope some questions are percolating
in everyone's minds here as you listen
to that.
It's absolutely fascinating.
Okay, so let's keep the tour rolling.
It would be amazing to see mission control
on the OceanXplorer.
Alexis, would you care to
give us the tour?
Yeah, absolutely. We'll head that way.
So it's going to take us
a little bit of time to get there.
So it's just a, kind of back,
back tour of part of the ship.
So you'll get to see a little bit
more of where operations are happening.
So we mentioned
earlier about having an ROV
or a remotely operated vehicle.
So our ROV is currently in the water
doing an active dive.
And so as we come through this area,
you'll be able to see
that the ROV is down
over the side of the ship
and it is connected to that wire,
that tether.
So you can see the ocean out there.
You can hopefully see the wire.
And then we're going to head into mission
control, where you can see what
the pilots and the scientists are seeing
while the ROV is exploring.
The weather looks pretty good today
Alexis?
Yeah, we're lucky today.
We have pretty good weather.
It can be a tough place to work
the Indian Ocean, but it's
very much cooperating with us right now.
So we're really fortunate.
So we're going to head in
to mission control.
So as you go in, you can see that
we have lots of people
working in here at the moment.
And so you can see in front of
these are all the screens
that the ROV pilots and the scientists
are using to understand what's happening
underwater with the ROV right now.
And then we're going
to walk around this way to give you guys
just a little bit different view.
Alexis, can you tell us what,
this the researchers
they are looking at on those screens,
the role mission control plays?
And tell us a little bit more
about how you use ROVs in your research?
Absolutely.
So first I'm going to kind of introduce
who is here right now.
So you guys can see the people in action.
We have two ROV pilots.
So we have Colin waving at you
and we have Ewan, our pilot,
over on the other side.
So their role is to make sure everything
that happens with the ROV is happening well.
They're engineers, they're pilots.
They have multiple roles on board
to make sure
that we're doing our operations safe.
And also like they're incredibly good
at doing their job.
So making sure that we get great video
and we get great samples.
And so what we're doing right now is
the scientists are in the back row.
Here are scientists
from the Western Australian Museum,
and they're leading in the dock
as meaning that they're helping,
they're telling the pilots
what they'd like to do,
what they'd like to look at,
and what they'd like to collect.
And that allows for them
to get the samples
that they're interested in from eDNA,
like Jen talked about, as well as
other collections that we bring back
on board and into the wet lab.
And so what they're looking at right now
on the screens is
they're looking at a coral right now,
which is my favorite topic.
And then they have
some brittle stars on top.
And you can see there's
a bunch of different screens
and that's so that they can see
what's happening all around the ROV,
because it's a robot that's essentially
at 3000m down on the seafloor right now.
And so we have six cameras
that allow us to look
at what's in front of the ROV,
what's underneath
the ROV, what's behind the ROV,
and what's on the left
and the right of the RV.
And then we also have
some other instruments and screens
that allow the pilots
to make sure
that all of the mechanics
are working well,
and that we know exactly where
the ROV is in relation to the ship.
So it's a it's a complicated, operation,
but this team has it,
has it down really well to make it
look easy and efficient.
And how does the ROV then
collect specimens?
If you see something that you'd like
to bring back to the vessel.
Yeah,
we have a couple different mechanisms.
And actually they're doing one right now.
So you can see Colin right here
has this up apparatus in his arms.
And so it is essentially
a small version of a large mechanical arm
that's on the ROV.
And so he's using that to control how
he's using that to control how
he is moving that arm underwater.
And what he has grasped in the arm
right now is what
we would call a suction sampler.
So it's a, it's a tube that will
we can use suction power to bring whatever
animal they're interested in getting,
and it'll bring it back into a chamber
that's located on the ROV.
Incredible.
And at that depth, at 3000m,
can you give us an idea
of the sort of the pressure
that the ROV would be under?
It's under immense pressure.
So one of the reasons that we use ROVs
is it's very difficult
to work in these conditions.
There are submersibles that can do that.
But when we get down
this deep, the pressure is so intense
that it requires
really, really specialized equipment
in order to work there.
So the ROV is unmanned,
meaning that it's a robot down there
operating from the guys doing it up
here, on the surface.
But there's nobody
physically in the, in the ROV.
Because what we're talking about here,
folks, is the deep ocean.
It's its largest
and least explored habitat.
More than seventy percent of it
remains unmapped and unexplored.
And we know less
about some deep sea environments
than we do about the surface of the moon.
How crazy is that?
Western Australia borders
the eastern reaches of the Indian Ocean,
the world's third largest ocean basin
and one of its
most environmentally diverse
marine regions.
The Indian Ocean encompasses vast
deep-sea landscapes,
including canyons,
seamounts, abyssal plains, and trenches.
These remote environments provide habitats
for remarkable species that have evolved
unique adaptations to survive
in conditions of complete darkness,
intense pressure, and extreme cold.
Jen, I want to talk a bit more about
how ROVs have made deep-sea
research possible.
Can you tell us about what it might see
at the depths
it's at today,
and what are you looking at?
So ROVs, of course, were
developed as part of the
oil and gas industry.
They used extensively for laying cables,
repairing of pipelines.
But in terms of science
that they're not used that extensively out
well certainly not in Australia.
So this opportunity for us to access
an ROV has been really,
you know, fantastic for us
because it gives us access
to habitat like this sort of rocky
sort of basalt environment that we wouldn't
otherwise be able to sample.
And you can see that...
Oh, I think we've lost, lost
Jen there for a second.
I'm sure we'll get her back.
But we can see incredible footage,
from the OceanXplorer
of how they get those samples
using the ROV.
... Incredible community of hard corals.
What have you seen?
You've seen something?
No? We saw a holothurian,
a beautiful
sea cucumber that I don't think
we've collected to date.
So I think, the staff were getting
a little bit excited.
So, yeah, really interesting communities,
that, we really weren't anticipating
a much more diverse and abundant
that, that we would ever have hoped.
So it's been very, it's
been incredibly fruitful for us
from a collections perspective
and an ability to be able to, you know,
bring these samples back to the Museum
for us to be able to study.
Jen, I can imagine
everybody would gather around the screens
there to see, you know,
what the ROV might discover.
Could you take us through
what it feels like when you see something
that is unknown that you haven't
come across before,
that might be completely new to science?
Yeah,
there's certainly that 'a-ha' moment you get
when you see something
that has these never, you know, you
know, is a is potentially a new species.
There is a little bit of whooping
and jumping in the air.
And you know when, when someone like
Alexis, who has got so much experience
working in the deep sea,
when she gets excited and,
you know, we're onto something which,
which we've seen around these seamounts
that we've been working on.
So to me, that's, that means a lot.
It means that, you know, we've
really been in some very special places.
And now because of the quality
of the camera work in this connection,
it looks like you could be in a,
in a high tech office anywhere on land.
But of course, you're out
on the high seas.
You're researching the deep ocean.
Alexis, can you give us an idea of
of some of the biggest challenges
that you must face
in the course of your work?
Yeah.
So we're really fortunate
to have a really fantastic vessel.
And we have really good,
you know, internet connection
now with kind of the development of,
better internet providers,
Starlink and things like that.
But over the years of doing this,
there's always different challenges
that come up with each mission.
One of them that is always out of our
control is weather and ocean currents.
So, you know, we have a capacity
to operate up to a certain weather window.
But sometimes
Mother Nature has other ideas
and we just have to be okay with that.
There's also always the complications.
We're working with really
high tech equipment.
So that requires having everybody on board
that could handle any complication
that comes up.
And so what the ship does is
it staffs in a way that we can repair
most anything, that we're to have an issue
while we're out here.
But sometimes it's something
that requires a new part
or we have to go back into port for.
So there's things like that
that are out of our control,
but we really do our best to
to come out with a team
that can kind of handle
any of the challenges that come our way.
And normally we can make,
we can make something work.
And now this
this might be a silly question, but
as someone who gets queasy on the
Rotto ferry, is being a marine
scientist,
does it sort of automatically self-select?
So if you get seasick,
you're probably just not going to be
in this field of research?
Or you learn
which medication works for you.
So there are there are folks
that you know, they know, they've learned,
but that they don't agree well with the
with the movement of the ship.
And so they figure out, you know,
how do they combat that?
Or they decide that they're going to do
the analysis on land,
so they send somebody else to come
do the work on the ship.
But the other is that
generally giving yourself three days or so
and you get your sea legs
so most people can acclimate after
after
just a little bit of time on the ship.
Oh, that's good to know.
And what's the what's the biggest swell
that you've, you've encountered?
We have had
maybe a couple metres on this expedition.
So nothing too crazy, but three metres
feels, you can feel it
when you're on the ship.
But yeah, there's other folks
that have been sailing for a long time,
and they could give you
some serious stories about having
to strap yourself into your bed
and things like that.
Oh my goodness.
Well, thank you
both for this very insightful tour, folks.
Can you put your hands together
for Jen and Alexis?
Okay.
So now I believe,
you're going to find somewhere comfortable
to sit in mission control
because it's time for the audience,
to ask the questions.
And so, folks, we're going to have
a microphone that we'll bring around.
So if you put your hand up,
we will come to you.
Wait till you've got the microphone.
So Jen and Alexis can hear you.
And, as a favor,
could you please just avoid
making any statements before the question?
Just ask the question so we can get
through as many questions as possible.
Because we do have a limited time,
with the gang on the ship.
So who wants to go first, madam
in the front?
Q: I'm just wondering if it's possible
to be a volunteer on such a
sort of scientific exploration vessel?
Volunteering
Wondering if it's possible?
So, because of our types of operations,
our ship is staffed
really specifically to, be able to cover
all of the different things that we do.
So we often don't have space, for anybody
that's not got a really specific job
while we're out here.
So while we love for people
to get involved however they can
normally on the vessel,
it's, it's trained professionals
so that we can make sure
we're utilizing our time well.
Q: Can you take a moment to explain what's going on behind you?
Okay. Yeah.
Somebody else quickly?
I'll say, Ben, behind us
you can see this screen.
This is the ROV feed right now.
So this is what the pilots
and the scientists are seeing.
So also, if people have questions
about what's going on, please feel free to ask.
So we see if we see something
that we think is
new to science behind you,
we'll just like turn around.
Yes.
Okay.
We've got another question.
Q: What was your first discovery?
You want to go?
Oh, that's, that's tricky.
So my first discovery.
Well, I discovered a new
species of fish in the,
in the Indian Ocean in the northwest
Indian Ocean.
I haven't named it yet,
but it's definitely a new species.
So that's very exciting to be able
to, to be able to, you know,
put a name to a species
that's very new to science.
Oh, Jen, I've got an idea for a name.
Why don't you call it
Ben, could you call it Ben?
Ben I.
Oh, yeah. Of course.
Okay.
Now we've got somebody else. Yep.
Q: How many species have you discovered?
That's a really good question.
So a lot of the time,
we don't know for certain
that something is new until a scientist
like the curators at WAM can spend
a good amount of time looking at it
and comparing it to other animals.
So we have discovered definitely,
you know, in the order
in the magnitude of a hundred new species
aboard the OceanXplorer.
But that number is always growing, as
we continue to do exploration like this.
Amazing.
Oh, we've got another one.
Q: How many seaweed
have you found in your explore
Seaweed?
Yeah.
Yeah. Seaweed.
We haven't seen a lot of seaweed.
You know, seaweed,
of course, requires a lot.
of light in order to live.
And in these very,
very deep environments, there is no light.
It's completely dark.
And so seaweed really
can't grow at 2 or 3 or 4000m
where we like
where we're working on board the ship.
So you'd have to you have to go up
into the sort of the shallow,
environments
in order to find and study seaweed.
Okay. Yeah. Somebody else?
Q: Hi, you said that you are taking samples
from 3000m below the sea surface.
How does it affect the sample
when you bring it up
the current air
pressure that we have here up on land?
Yeah, that's also a really great question.
So, there, like I said, there's immense
pressure down there.
But most of the sampling
that we do is of either
sediments, water or invertebrate animals.
And so they don't actually
have much,
the pressure doesn't impact them because
they have no air within their bodies.
And so when you bring them up, they
they still look the same.
They still have the same structure.
But when we work with fish,
that can be a different story.
So the fish, we want to make sure
we bring them up in a humane way,
and we work with them
so that when we preserve them,
they are going through a process
that, that isn't harmful to the fish.
And also, the other thing I'd like to add
is that the nature of this
and the beauty about working with an RV
is it's highly selective.
And, it means that we take
only a very few number
of samples of the species
that we're interested in.
And, and that's really important to us.
So we're not harming the environment
in any way because we're taking
and you can see
just how many animals, you know,
we'll often just take a photograph.
And so you can see just how abundant
a lot of these animals are.
And we've taken just very few samples
on this particular dive.
Yeah.
It's helpful just for context with
what Jen's saying, is that, like the camera,
as Ben said earlier, are so high quality
and so high resolution
that if we get one,
one representative of the physical sample,
that means that we can
then look at the video
and compare it
to the other ones that we see,
and it allows us to identify them
just on the imagery.
I hope you guys are comfortable,
because there's a lot of kids here, and I
can see a lot of hands up in the audience,
some in the front row as well.
Alicia, you've got
somebody else with a question.
Q: Hi. I have two questions.
The first one,
have you found any DNA samples of,
species that you thought were,
that we think had gone extinct?
And the second question is,
do you have an onboard medic?
Yeah, yeah. So I'll start with number two.
We do have an onboard medic.
So we always sail with,
somebody who sails as a medical officer.
So they're trained, to handle
anything that might happen.
And then for discovering things
that might be extinct.
We have had some studies where we detect
really interesting DNA that I can't quite
speak about, but we definitely are often
finding kind of the unexpected
in the DNA samples that we, that we sequence.
Yeah.
So the eDNA, the water samples
would certainly pick up DNA of things
like whales, big marine mammals, dolphins,
so that's the beauty about it.
It can it can detect DNA without having
to harm those animals in any way.
And so when you collect
this DNA,
you're comparing it to existing samples
that are, say, in the WA Museum's collection,
what happens if you come across something
that isn't
in the collection?
Yeah.
That's a, that's a
that's a really good question.
That doesn't happen very often because we
we have a we have a pretty extensive,
collection to that end.
And so it what would what would happen
in that particular instance
is that the geneticists
would then go and look at a global library
of DNA sequences to try and track it down,
to see if they can actually,
you know, so there are these global
databases that they can tap into and,
and use and screen for, for the animals
that they're detecting with DNA.
If in fact, you know,
we're unable to help them.
Yeah.
And one of the things that is
is interesting with eDNA,
especially in the oceans,
is that when you create the sequences
and you're looking at and trying
to match them back to those databases,
so what are known sequences and have,
a species identified with them?
There's actually
a high percentage of that total DNA
that has no match, because we haven't
collected a sample of it
somewhere in the world before.
So that's
where continuing to do the collections
alongside the eDNA is really important,
because every collection
we make improves that detection ability.
And with our folks from OceanOmics,
they were talking about before that,
you know,
they've done comparative studies to
if they're just sequencing
based on global data and comparing
to global databases versus this type
of pairing situation where we bring
samples back
from the area
that they're collecting their water eDNA,
they have a much higher rate
of those detections,
matching something
that they were collecting in that time.
Now we've got someone in the front row
who's been waiting to ask a question.
Take it away.
Q: How many, how much pollution
and microplastics have you seen since
you started your expedition?
That's a really good question.
We actually haven't seen a ton of
of plastic
or anything that's large
enough for us to see on the seafloor.
But there have been a number of studies
that show that unfortunately,
there is a lot of microplastic,
kind of all over the ocean at this point.
So we are always keeping an eye out
and we try and document that,
those types of observations
when we see them,
so we can have an understanding
of how people are impacting these systems.
Okay.
>> Next?
>> Q: Have you ever been in the submersible
and if so, how scary is it?
I have had the chance to go
in our submersible
and then and in a couple others also.
And I for me, it's not scary.
For me, it's probably the most exciting
moment of my life.
It's the really amazing experience
to get to go down
and observe the deep sea in real time.
ROVs are really useful for their utility,
but there's kind of
nothing like the experience
of being in the, in the space yourself.
Gives you a whole different perspective
for what these habitats
and ecosystems look like.
And, and there are two submarine,
technicians on board
OceanX, the incredibly
well trained, the,
the submersibles are
maintained to a very high standard.
And so they're very, very safe to that and,
and they have a maximum depth range of down
to about 1000m.
So no deeper than that.
And now I've got a question
from a little girl
who's had her arm up so high
and so straight,
I think she's going to need a physio
after she asks this question.
What's your question?
Q: My question is
how many sea animals have you seen?
That's a really good question because
we've seen a lot of sea animals.
So we are doing these ROV dives
for about a whole day at a time.
So we'll, we will send the ROV
down to the seafloor in the morning.
And then it explores all day.
So even today, we've probably seen,
thousands of sea animals
that are on the seafloor.
And, and then we also
are looking at plankton.
So really small sea animals
that are in the water.
When that we're looking at what's
in the surface of the water too.
While we're just looking at the screen there
and seeing the ROV.
I've actually got a question
that's come in
from Christmas Island,
from the audience dialing in from there,
their question is, did deep sea creatures
ever show interest in the ROV?
Do they swim up to it?
Have they ever attacked it?
Do they? Often they're
actually, they're not...
They're normally
not that interested in us.
So one of the things that is on the ROV
that we didn't talk about
are a lot of lights.
So as Jen said earlier,
this is an area of the ocean
that normally is in complete darkness.
So things like fish that do have eyes,
they don't love that
we're shining bright lights on them,
so they tend to kind of go the other way.
But we sometimes see crabs and squat
lobsters like this little guy right here,
and they will definitely
put their claws up
and tell us to stay away
if we get too close.
Yeah.
Oh, and then we have ...
Ewan our ROV
pilot is hearing the questions and chiming
in that the ROV has been attacked
or approached by a swordfish before.
>> Three different swordfish.
>> So. three different swordfish.
Oh, that's exciting because I think
the people in Christmas Island,
maybe they've seen a Jason Statham movie,
The giant The Meg.
If there's one of those down there,
I don't know?
And we have a question here
in the audience with us at the Museum.
Q: Have you ever seen a live oarfish before?
A live oarfish?
>> No, I have not.
>> I have not, and I would be
I would love to see one,
but I have never seen one.
Oarfish?
Okay?
>> Ewan has, to know that it
>> A juvenile.
He's seen a juvenile oarfish.
When you think about
who has the most experience looking at
what's in the ocean, it's our ROV pilots
because they do this every mission.
Yeah.
Amazing.
Okay, another question from the audience.
Q: What is the weirdest looking species
you've ever seen?
What do you think?
I, I think some of the, some of the fish
that we're seeing on this
on this expedition, because they're
so unusual that they're often long bodied,
they look eel-like, the conger the,
the,
conger eels and yeah,
they're extraordinary looking animals
that live in very cold,
very dark environments.
So they're probably my favorite, I think.
But that's I'm a bit biased
because I'm a fish person, so
I think one of mine is
we saw one today earlier,
which is it's known as a 'sea spider',
but it's called a pycnogonid.
So it's a type of crustacean,
actually, that
looks like a spider with its long legs
and it creeps around.
But they're quite, they're quite strange.
Oh, wow. There's something.
What is that?
Is that what's behind you right now?
That is a squat lobster.
So that's it's related to a crab.
And these ones are, we've been
seeing them kind of in this region
and quite a bit where they're
white like that and they have two claws,
and then they have a tail, kind of
like a shrimp, but it tucks it under.
So, when they swim,
they actually swim backwards.
If we, you might see it,
if they end up spooking it.
That's a, and that's a glass sponge.
Yeah. That, that they're living on.
Yeah. Wow. Okay. Next?
Q: Will you ever go to them Ariana Trench?
The, the Marianas Trench?
Yes? No.
>> Oh no. Have, has OceanX?
>> I have not, I, I don't think OceanX has.
I personally have not,
but there is other, there are other groups
doing exploration in that area right now.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Next.
Q: How long does it take
to get to the bottom of the ocean?
Yeah that's a really good question.
So the ROV descends at a certain speed.
And so for us to get down to about 28,
2800, 2900m ... Hey, Ewan?
>> So to get to a full operating
depth of 6000m
takes about two and a half
to two and three quarter hours.
So if we were going down to as deep
as we are, we could go, which is 6000m.
So double where we're at today.
It takes about three hours to get there.
So for us,
it took us about an hour and a half
for the ROV
to get to this depth this morning.
Yeah. Wow.
I've got another question
from Christmas Island.
They want to know more about seamounts
in the ocean,
why they have such biodiversity?
Yeah.
So seamounts
are essentially underwater mountains.
And so if you think about the terrain
of the seafloor,
those mountains are made up of hard rock
or a hard surface.
And so the areas in between the mountains
are what we call abyssal plain.
And that's often soft sediment.
So that's where all of that
debris has fallen down.
And what we found is that most of these,
like what we call benthic communities
or animals that live
kind of on the surface of rocks,
they really like seamounts
because they provide that habitat,
which is a place that they settle
and then they grow
because they're not moving around.
And so what we've,
what the scientific community
has kind of started to understand
is that seamounts provide
these kind of hotspots across the world's
oceans for these communities to exist.
Even if there's
not land nearby
or other, other types of input.
I've got another question
from someone here at the Museum.
Q: What is your favorite species of coral?
>> Oh, there we go.
>> That's my favourite question.
I wish I could show you a picture.
My favorite species
or group of coral are called bubblegum
corals because they're bright pink
and they're very beautiful.
>> Really pretty.
But they can live really deep
in, in the ocean as well as
and they're very old, right?
Yeah.
They can grow, most of the species that
live in the deep ocean grow very slowly.
And they live to be very old.
So the oldest coral ever age-dated
is over 4000 years old.
So, these are quite, quite ancient
animals.
Well, this might be a question for you, Jen.
It's come
all the way from Christmas Island.
Q: How long does it take to train
as a taxonomist to do the works
that, the staff at the museum
and scientists are doing?
So, most of our curators,
have PhDs,
so they usually do an undergraduate degree
in marine science, and then they'll go on
and either doing an honours or a master's.
So that's sort of anywhere
from 4 to 5 years.
And then they'll go on
and do a PhD, which usually takes anywhere
from 3 to 4 years.
And then they might do what
we call a postdoctoral fellowship,
which is another year or two after that.
So yeah, a fair chunk of time,
I would say, anywhere
from sort of 7 to 9 years.
Yeah. Wow.
And we've got a question here
from the kids at the front.
Q: How long has OceanX been
an exploring company?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So the ship started exploring in 2021.
So we have been kind of
continuously exploring different parts
of the world's oceans,
for the last five years or so.
I think we have time
for maybe one more question.
Q: How many ammonite fossils
have you found starting from?
today?
We haven't,
so we haven't found any ammonite fossils.
But on a previous expedition we did see
when we were around the waters of Palau,
which is in the Pacific,
we saw live Nautilus,
which are essentially
the descendants of ammonites.
Yeah,
yeah. Wow.
Okay, folks, sadly,
that's all we have time for today.
Can you please put your hands together
and thank our scientists
Dr Alexis Weinnig and Dr Jen McIlwain?
Thanks you guys.
Thanks.
Thanks, Jen
and Alexis. It's been so great to
to hear from you and hear about your work.
Really appreciate your time today.
Thank you so much.
And on behalf of all of us here
at the WA Museum Boola Bardip
I'd like to thank everybody who joined us
for this special event today.
From those who dialed
in from Christmas Island
and the audience here in Hackett Hall.
Just a reminder that the OceanXperience
exhibition is running through to October 11
this year.
So make sure you check it out.
And if you've already seen it,
tell your friends.
Make sure they come down and see it too,
because we'd love to welcome them.
Okay, folks,
that's it. It's goodbye from us.
Please make sure you get home safe.
Okay?
Bye bye.
#music plays